Guide to the Vincent McHugh Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- March 2002 Acquisition, 1933-1983; 1; 58.3; (70 boxes)
  - Writings
    - Greek Plays and Guggenheim, 1956 January 5, undated (Box 47)
    - Delta - General, newspaper clippings, 1963 (Box 47)
    - Manuscript notes from A Long Way, 1937 November 17, undated; 2 (Box 47)
    - Against Nature review, undated (Box 47)
    - Newspaper clippings, empty envelopes, various writings, 1958-1960, undated (Box 47)
    - Unsorted writings, 1958-1959, undated (Box 47)
    - San Francisco earthquake article, 1960 (Box 47)
    - "The Whopper Scrapbook", undated
      Contains clippings of writings by McHugh
    - New People / New World, undated (Box 48)
    - Caleb Catlum's America, 1940 (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 2 (Box 48)
    - Newport, undated; 4 (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1958, undated; 4 (Box 48)
  - Professional Papers
    Organized under six headings: Lecture, Course, and Teaching Materials; The Works Progress Administration; Office of War Information Films; Writer's War Board; Paramount Picture; and Other Papers.
    - Lectures, Course, and Teaching Materials
      - Creative writing class: pieces by students, 1950, undated (Box 49)
      - AP class material, undated (Box 49)
      - Fort Collins lecture, undated (Box 49)
      - AP workshop, 1958 (Box 49)
      - Creative writing class notes, undated (Box 49)
      - Writing II: session notes, [1950] (Box 49)
      - Bank dialogues, undated (Box 49)
      - Notes on the Great Gatsby, undated (Box 49)
      - Boulder, [1949] (Box 49)
      - Writing III: session notes, [1952] (Box 49)
      - Durham Writer's Conference: Text from Balzac, 1949 July 15 (Box 49)
      - Toward a Theory of Approach in Adult Education, 1950 (Box 49)
      - Imagination class, 1951 July 26 (Box 49)
      - Kansas City lecture notes, undated (Box 49)
      - Rupe: novel, undated (Box 49)
      - Columbia lecture notes, undated (Box 49)
      - Notes for Framing Talk, 1950 May 15 (Box 49)
      - The Tiger and the Jackal, undated (Box 49)
      - The Future is a Guessing Game, 1949 August 1 (Box 49)
      - Talk on writing, undated (Box 49)
      - Lecture, 1939 December 20 (Box 49)
      - Various course outlines, 1948 March 30, undated (Box 49)
      - Notes: The Popular Arts, undated (Box 49)
      - Course list and descriptions, 1948 (Box 49)
      - Various lecture material, undated (Box 49)
      - Theory Practice course, 1950 Fall (Box 49)
      - American Novel, 1947, undated; 2 (Box 49)
      - Novel charts, undated (Box 49)
      - Lecture: How Many Roads to Banbury Cross?, 1952 July 3 (Box 49)
      - Dos Passos lecture material, 1949 February 17, undated (Box 49)
      - New View of Japan, undated (Box 50)
      - The Fun Country, 1966 (Box 50)
      - Lecture: Jazz and American Culture, 1951 August 20 (Box 50)
      - Contemporary literature class, 1951 September, undated (Box 50)
      - How the Arts Affect Social Change, undated (Box 50)
      - A Program for Standardization and Simplification of Supplies in the Hospital, undated (Box 50)
      - Lecture: Sources of Process in the Novel, 1950 July 14 (Box 50)
      - Lecture: Freedom and Authority, 1951 January 24; 2 (Box 50)
      - Lecture notes: Freedom and Authority, 1951 January 24 (Box 50)
      - Prospectus, 1950 November 5 (Box 50)
      - Novel course / Writing courses, 1951 July, undated (Box 50)
      - Durham, 1950-1951 (Box 50)
      - Lecture: Dominant Trends of the Half-Century: The Novel, 1950 October 15 (Box 50)
      - Lecture: The Victory: Genesis of a Novel, 1949 May 4 (Box 50)
      - Notes for talk, 1949 April 23 (Box 50)
      - The Romantic Writer and the Medieval Publisher, undated (Box 50)
      - Comments on student pieces, 1949-1950 (Box 50)
      - Student papers and correspondence regarding student work, 1950s (Box 50)
    - The Works Progress Administration
      - Supplementary Instructions # 15 to the American Guide Manual, 1936 September 15 (Box 51)
      - Supplementary Instructions # 10 to the American Guide Manual, Appendix C, 1936 September 10 (Box 51)
      - American Guide Manual, undated (Box 51)
      - Supplementary Instructions # 9 - D to the American Guide Manual, 1936, October 24 (Box 51)
      - Supplementary Instructions # 16 to American Guide Manual, [1936 October 27] (Box 51)
      - Supplementary Instructions # 11 to the American Guide Manual, Appendix A, 1936, May 5 (Box 51)
      - Supplementary Instructions # 15-A to American Guide Manual, 1937 November 9 (Box 51)
      - What the Federal Writers Project Is Doing, undated (Box 51)
      - New York City guide book, undated (Box 51)
      - Look Behind You by Manly Wade Wellman, undated (Box 51)
    - Office of War Information Films
      - Detroit, 1973 (Box 52)
      - OWI papers, 1943 (Box 52)
      - Desert Films: Australia or Defenders of Tobruk, undated (Box 52)
      - Merchant Marine, undated (Box 52)
      - On the Line, 1943 January 28 (Box 52)
      - On Freedom of Speech, 1943 January (Box 52)
      - Epidemic Control and the War, 1943 (Box 52)
      - Action in the Sand, 1943 (Box 52)
      - Quartermaster's War, 1943 March 5 (Box 52)
      - Industrial Recreation, 1943 August 6 (Box 52)
      - Caribbean Alert, 1943 May (Box 52)
      - A Yankee Ship Went Down the River, undated (Box 52)
      - Soldier from the Tropic, 1943 July 27, undated; 9 (Box 52)
      - On Freedom of Religion, 1943 January 5 (Box 52)
      - On Freedom from Fear, 1943 January 29 (Box 52)
      - Carrier, 1943 April 1, undated (Box 52)
    - Writer's War Board
      - War Shipping Administration, undated (Box 52)
      - Tour Information and Things To See, undated (Box 52)
      - The Name is De Paris, undated (Box 52)
      - Dear Joe, 1943 Winter (Box 52)
      - Transatlantic: State of the States, undated (Box 52)
    - Paramount Pictures
      - Child of Nature, undated (Box 52)
      - Singing on the River, 1944 April 14, undated (Box 52)
      - Rags to Riches, 1944 April 25 (Box 52)
      - Notes on scripts, undated (Box 52)
      - Practically Yours, 1944; 3 (Box 52)
      - Scripts / Movie suggestions, undated (Box 52)
      - Princess of the Warpath, 1944 (Box 52)
      - Walking on Air, 1944 April 20 (Box 52)
    - Other Papers
      - National Book Award material, 1969; 2 (Box 53)
      - National Translation Center, 1967-1969; 9 (Box 53)
  - Personal Papers
    - Bills, circa 1935-1979, undated; 27 (Box 54)
    - Bills, circa 1935-1979, undated; 29 (Box 55)
    - Voucher, 1968 (Box 55)
    - Income Tax, 1948 (Box 55)
    - Social Security material, 1969-1971, undated; 2 (Box 55)
    - Travel expense vouchers, 1940; 3 (Box 56)
    - Japan, 1968; 2 (Box 56)
    - Japan trip itinerary, 1965 (Box 56)
    - Japan trip, undated; 2 (Box 56)
    - Typed letter from Vincent McHugh to Mrs. Churchill, 1952 February 24 (Box 56)
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 56)
    - Japan trip, 1965 (Box 56)
    - Obituaries, 1964-1993 (Box 56)
    - First transcription of 4 autobiographical tapes, circa 1973 (Box 56)
    - Holiday Chinatown, 1960 April 18, undated (Box 56)
    - Tsung Tsin constitution, undated (Box 56)
    - Scratch paper, undated; 4 (Box 56)
    - Financial documents, 1944, undated (Box 56)
    - One line drawings by McHugh, undated (Box 56)
    - Matchbooks, undated; 2 (Box 56)
    - Blank postcards, undated; 7 (Box 56)
  - Journals and Notebooks
    - Journals and notebooks, 1949 -1953; 37 (Box 57)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1953-1956; 35 (Box 58)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1956-1960; 36 (Box 59)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1960-1972; 37 (Box 60)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 11 (Box 61)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 11 (Box 62)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 18 (Box 63)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 33 (Box 64)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 37 (Box 65)
    - Journals and notebooks, 1948-1972, undated; 28 (Box 66)
  - Photographs
    A list of selected photographs provided by the vendor is filed in box 67.
    - Unsorted photographs, undated; 3 (Box 67)
    - Photograph of unidentified woman, undated (Box 67)
    - Photographic slides
      - Kyoto general / Yasaka before festival / Chigo-San / Kyoto Kaikan, undated (Box 67)
      - Shine processions, undated (Box 67)
      - Floats and Yoi-Yama, undated (Box 67)
      - Hanagasa / Yasaka processions, undated (Box 67)
      - Yamaboko / Hanagasa / Shine processions, undated (Box 67)
      - Heron dancers / Deneaku-No, undated (Box 67)
      - Yamaboko, undated (Box 67)
  - Sound Recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 68 (audiotape reels): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Box 69 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "The Women of Lemnos". Vincent McHugh speaking the prologue of his verse poem. (1 of 3), 1953 June 12; 1; 00:25:09 (Box 68, Item barcode 39002109972191)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "The Women of Lemnos". Vincent McHugh speaking, Scene 1, Act I of his verse play (2 of 3), 1953 June 12; 1; 00:22:43 (Box 68, Item barcode 39002109972209)
    - "The Women of Lemnos". Vincent McHugh speaking, Scene 2, Act I of his verse play (3 of 3), 1953 June 12; 1; 00:21:16 (Box 68, Item barcode 39002109972183)
    - "Five Poems", undated; 1; 00:10:18; A high amount of hum and hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 68, Item barcode 39002109972217)
    - Vincent McHugh reading, undated; 1; 00:30:04; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The volume fluctuates throughout the program. There is silence from 9:30 to 11:05. (Box 68, Item barcode 39002109972225)
    - "Vincent McHugh Autobiography no. 1" (1 of 4), 1973 July 14; 1; 01:01:54; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973272)
    - "Vincent McHugh Autobiography no. 2" (2 of 4), 1973 July; 1; 00:31:13; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard. Static is present on the tape as well. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973280)
    - "Vincent McHugh Autobiography no. 3" (3 of 4), 1973 July; 1; 01:01:31; High background noise and static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973298)
    - "Vincent McHugh Autobiography no. 4" (4 of 4), 1973 July; 1; 00:32:22; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973264)
    - "Chinese Poetry". Vincent McHugh reading his translations / "Songs", Arnold Cheung singing, San Francisco, 1958; 1; 00:09:11; High amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973371)
    - Vincent McHugh reading from his "Mutabilities", 1981 July 25; 1; 00:12:17 (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973322)
    - "Women of Lemnos". Prologue, Act I, Scene 1 (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1953 June 12; 1; 00:47:53; The program speeds up at the beginning of the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973355)
    - "Women of Lemnos". Act I, Scene 2 (2 of 2), 1953 June 12; 1; 00:21:05 (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973348)
    - Vincent McHugh reading his poetry, 1981 July 25; 1; 01:01:47; High background noise and static can be heard on the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973314)
    - "Songs by John Duke (at piano)" / "Five poems by Vincent McHugh", 1970; 1; 00:10:14; Audio sounds weak or hollow at times. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973330)
    - "Poetry" Vincent McHugh reading Geoffrey, Stephens, Raftery, etc. / "Brief account by Esther Leuenberger (sister of Vincent McHugh) of going to Block Island when McHugh lived there", 1983 March; 1; 00:36:14; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. A warble can be heard on the first 30 seconds of the tape. Weak or hollow-sounding audio can also be heard. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973306)
    - "Songs & Blues", Vincent McHugh and Thomas Ferril / continuation of Mechau Family Ballads, 1950; 1; 00:50:17; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973389)
      A list of contents is included with this audiocassette.
      Nameless Air (3 versions each)
      Lily of Dotsero
      Wrangler's Song
      Burnt R. Blues
      Snowy Blues
      Redbird Blues
    - Vincent McHugh reciting poetry, 1969; 1; 00:16:11; High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 69, Item barcode 39002109973363)
  - Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
    - "The Whopper Scrapbook", undated (Box 70)
- October 2003 Acquisition, 1949-1978; 2; 0.42; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 586
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1949-1978; 2 (Box 71)
  - Address books and notebooks, 1965 July 22, undated; 4 (Box 71)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 71)
  - Passport and international vaccination booklets, [1965] (Box 71)
  - Business cards and identification cards, undated; 4 (Box 71)
- July 2005 Acquisition, 1963; 3; 0.21; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat Za File 699
  - Drawings (reproductions) of Vincent McHugh by Patricia McHugh, [1963] (Box 72)